{"tossups": [{"question": "The Soviet Union boycotted this event in favor of their own Spartakiad to be hosted in Barcelona the following year. The reporters of <em>Der St\u00fcrmer</em> [[SHTIR-muh]] were banned from the host city during this procession. Prior to this event, Adidas founder Adolf Dassler convinced Jesse Owens to wear his shoes prior to the Long Jump competition. For ten points, name this 1936 athletic event hosted by the government of Adolf Hitler in the German capital.", "answer": "<b><u>Berlin Olympic</u></b>s (accept <b><u>1936 Olympics</u></b> before \"1936\"; prompt on \"Nazi Olympics\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A representative from this U.S. state spit tobacco juice in the face of Connecticut politician Roger Griswold. This home-state of Matthew Lyon was primarily led during its time as an independent republic by Thomas Chittenden. This was the first state outside of the Thirteen Colonies to ratify the U.S. Constitution and was home to Ethan Allen and the Green Mountain Boys. For ten points, name this New England state once claimed by New Hampshire.", "answer": "<b><u>Vermont</u></b> (accept <b><u>Vermont</u></b> Republic; or R\u00e9publique du <b><u>Vermont</u></b>; accept State of <b><u>Vermont</u></b>; or \u00c9tat du <b><u>Vermont</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A follower of the priest Iliodor [[ill-YOH-dor]] attempted to assassinate this man by stabbing him in the stomach. Another attempted assassination of this man involved feeding him cyanide-laced cake before he was finally killed with a bullet to the head by Felix Yusupov. This holy man claimed to have cured Alexei Romanov of hemophilia. For ten points, name this Russian mystic whose influence grew due to his closeness with Empress Alexandra.", "answer": "Grigori Yefimovich <b><u>Rasputin</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Romano-British syncretized this deity with the Celtic figure Sulis, forming a duo who protected over the thermal waters of Bath. This goddess, whom the Etruscans showed uncharacteristically hurling lightning bolts, was often depicted in fresco reliefs with a lowered sword as opposed to her more vicious parallel, Mars. For ten points, which Roman goddess of wisdom and war's Greek analogue is Athena?", "answer": "<b><u>Minerva</u></b> (accept <b><u>Menrva</u></b>; do not accept \"Athena\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "Over 300 eunuchs and maids died in this city's Old Summer Palace following its intentional burning by the British under Lord Elgin. Prince Gong signed an 1860 treaty named for this city, ceding parts of Manchuria to Russia and leasing Kowloon to Britain. Following the Northern Expedition, central authority was moved south from this city to Nanjing. The Forbidden City is located in, for ten points, what modern capital of China?", "answer": "<b><u>Beijing</u></b> (or <b><u>Beiping</u></b>; accept <b><u>Peking</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In Islamic tradition, this figure will kill the malevolent <em>ad-Dajjal</em> [[ahd-dah-JAHL]] and both Gog and Magog during the Second Coming. The Cathedral of Turin houses a shroud supposedly bearing the face of this man, whose execution apparatus was split into several pieces that are considered relics in the Christian church. For ten points, name this holy figure who was executed under Roman law in Judea, being nailed to the True Cross.", "answer": "<b><u>Jesus</u><u>Christ</u></b> (accept either underlined portion; accept <b><u>Isa</u></b> ibn Maryam; or <b><u>Yeshua</u></b> bar Joseph)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "A congratulatory email sent to this man was allegedly one of only two emails sent by Bill Clinton during his presidency. Though not John McCain, this man\u2019s acceptance of a $200,000 loan made him a member of the Keating Five. A record three-and-a-half hour flight from L.A. to New York was conducted by this man before being chosen as a member of the Mercury Seven. The lone occupant on a five-hour flight in 1962 aboard <em>Friendship 7</em>, for ten points, who was this astronaut, the first American to orbit the Earth?", "answer": "John <b><u>Glenn</u></b> (or John Herschel <b><u>Glenn</u></b> Jr.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In his treatise, <em>Thoughts on Government</em>, this man wrote that \u201cPolitics is the Science of human happiness.\u201d As a member of the Second Continental Congress, this man predicted that American independence would be celebrated on July 2nd. As a lawyer, this man successfully defended Thomas Preston and the other British soldiers who perpetrated the Boston Massacre. For ten points, name this Massachusetts statesman who also served as the first vice president and second president of the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>J</u></b>ohn <b><u>Adams</u></b> (do not accept \"John Quincy Adams\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city behind the Warwick Line was defended in a siege by Confederate John B. McGruder during the Peninsular Campaign of the U.S. Civil War. This city is one of three sites on Virginia\u2019s Historic Triangle, along with Williamsburg and Jamestown. Redoubt 10 at this site was assaulted by Alexander Hamilton, and it fell after a blockade by the forces of the Comte de Grasse. For ten points, name this town that was the site of Cornwallis\u2019s 1781 surrender during the American Revolutionary War.", "answer": "<b><u>Yorktown</u></b>, Virginia (accept Battle of <b><u>Yorktown</u></b>; or Siege of <b><u>Yorktown</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Though Milton Obote [[oh-BOH-teh]] was restored to this country's presidency after a brief war with Tanzania, he did not restore its traditional kingdoms such as Ankole [[ahn-KOH-leh]]. Obote's predecessor proclaimed himself Conqueror of the British Empire and expelled this country's Asian population while declaring himself King of Scotland. During that dictator's rule, Israel rescued over 100 hostages from this country in Operation Entebbe [[en-TEH-beh]]. For ten points, name this country, once ruled by Idi Amin.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Uganda</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 2021, the U.S. Supreme Court ruled in favor of two people of this profession who argued workers could not unionize on their property. After the U.S. Civil War, people of this profession formed the Grange advocacy group. Thomas Jefferson called people with this profession \"the chosen people of God,\" and this profession was one of the most severely affected by the Dust Bowl. For ten points, name this profession involved in growing crops and raising animals for consumption.", "answer": "<b><u>Farm</u></b>ers (accept word forms; accept <b><u>Agriculturist</u></b>; accept <b><u>Horticulturist</u></b>; prompt on \"rancher\" or \"gardener\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One account of this conflict ends at the Battle of Ascalon, where Godfrey of Bouillon [[boo-YOHN]] drove off the army of the Fatimids. Seljuk leader Kilij [[kee-LEEJ]] Arslan's lightly armored horse archers were defeated in this conflict by a combined Italo-Norman force at Dorylaeum [[DOR-ee-LAY-uhm]]. A Byzantine request for aid led to, for ten points, what 11th century war to recapture of the Holy Land from Muslim control?", "answer": "<b><u>First</u></b> Crusade (accept <b><u>Princes' Crusade</u></b>; prompt on \"Crusade\" or \"the Crusades\"; do not accept \"The People's Crusade\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "He is best known for possibly being the source of the rallying cry \"Deus Vult!\" or \"God wills it!\"", "answer": "Pope <b><u>Urban II</u></b> (accept <b><u>Odo of Ch\u00e2tillon</u></b>; accept <b><u>Otho de Lagery</u></b>; prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This country's first president, Guadalupe Victoria, was among only a few of its early leaders to complete a full term. One president of this nation engineered an eighth term as president in 1910, leading to his overthrow by Francisco Madero and a ten-year civil war. Benito Ju\u00e1rez [[HWAH-rehz]] governed this country, but was overthrown by an Austrian archduke. Emperor Maximilian was executed after failing to conquer, for ten points, what country where Cinco de Mayo commemorates a victory over France?", "answer": "<b><u>Mexico</u></b> (accept <b><u>U</u></b>nited <b><u>M</u></b>exican <b><u>S</u></b>tates, <b><u>Mexican</u></b> Empire, or <b><u>E</u></b>stados <b><u>U</u></b>nidos <b><u>M</u></b>exicanos)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "John Boehner [[BAY-ner]] resigned from this position in 2015 following a speech from Pope Francis the day prior. This position is second in the U.S. line of succession following the vice president. The current holder of this position represents the 12th District of California and went viral for a GIF of her clapping at Donald Trump in 2019. For ten points, name this elected leader of the lower chamber of the U.S. Congress, which is currently held by Nancy Pelosi.", "answer": "<b><u>Speaker of the House</u></b> of Representatives", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "During the 1904 Olympic iteration of one of these events in St. Louis, Cuban mailman Andar\u00edn Carvajal [[kar-vah-HAHL]] took a nap after breaking a forty hour fast by eating rotten apples. The Chechen-descended Tsarnaev [[zar-\"NIGH\"-yef]] brothers targeted the 2013 Boston iteration of these sporting events by using homemade bombs. The legendary run of Pheidippides [[fy-DIH-peh-deez]] from a battle site to Athens inspired, for ten points, what long-distance running events?", "answer": "<b><u>Marathon</u></b>s (accept Olympic <b><u>marathon</u></b>; accept Boston <b><u>marathon</u></b>; accept Battle of <b><u>Marathon</u></b>; prompt on more generic answers like \"long distance running\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This island attempted to secede from one country after the \"Grito de Lares\" [[GREE-toh deh LAH-rehs]]. This non-Cuban island was controlled by the Spanish since the defeat of the native Ta\u00edno [[tah-EE-noh]] by Juan Ponce de Le\u00f3n, who became this island's first governor. This island became a \"Commonwealth\" in 1952, and movements for full integration and independence have competed since then. For ten points, name this Caribbean territory of the United States, a potential 51st state.", "answer": "Commonwealth of <b><u>Puerto Rico</u></b> (accept Estado Libre Asociado de <b><u>Puerto Rico</u></b>; or <b><u>Boriken</u></b>; or <b><u>Borinquen</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This region's eastern part was split off as the Union Territory of Ladakh, and its northernmost frontiers, far from its capital Srinagar, are governed as Gilgit-Baltistan [[GIL-git BAHL-tee-stahn]]. This region's inhabitants were separated after a 1947 war that reflected tensions between its Maharaja Hari Singh and this region's majority-Muslim population. With a Line of Control between two parts of this region ending at the Siachen [[see-AH-chen]] Glacier, for ten points, what is this region which is disputed by India and Pakistan?", "answer": "<b><u>Kashmir</u></b> (accept Jammu and <b><u>Kashmir</u></b> Valley)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This man failed to pay a 500 <em>lira</em> bet with Duke Caetani [[cah-eh-TAH-nee]] after losing a sporting event against <em>butteri</em> Augusto Imperiali while on tour in Italy. This man and an organization named for him were denied entry into the 1893 World's Fair, so he set up his show directly outside the fairgrounds. This man's show included reenactments of bison hunts, the Battle of Little Bighorn, and the charge up San Juan Hill. For ten points, name this figure, the owner of a \"Wild West\" show which included figures like Sitting Bull and Annie Oakley.", "answer": "<b><u>Buffalo Bill</u></b> (accept William Frederick <b><u>Cody</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>The negotiation of the Suez Crisis was done by a diplomat from this political</u></b> <b><u>party, Lester Pearson. The Shawinigan [[shah-WEH-neh-gehn]] (+)</u> Handshake, which was a chokehold against a protestor by a leader of this party, occurred during anti-poverty protests in Gatineau [[gah-tee-NOW]], Quebec. Pierre and Justin (*) </b>Trudeau both served as leaders of, for ten points, which Canadian political party, the traditional opponents of the Conservatives?", "answer": "<b><u>Liberal</u></b> Party of Canada (accept Parti <b><u>lib\u00e9ral</u></b> du Canada)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The initial plans for the construction of this building were created by the</u></b> <b><u>Bethlehem Engineering Corporation which wanted to build an office complex at the</u></b> <b><u>site of a Waldorf-Astoria hotel. To complete this project, one of its investors, John J.</u></b> <b><u>Raskob, (+)</u> obtained a $27.5 million loan from the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company during the Great Depression. From 1931 to the completion of the World (*) </b>Trade Center in 1970, this building held the title of \"tallest in the world.\" For ten points, name this 102-story Art Deco skyscraper in midtown Manhattan.", "answer": "<b><u>Empire State</u></b> Building", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "<b><u>Attempts to suppress news of this document were countered by a group of</u></b> <b><u>secret messengers called the 4Ls. This document specifically exempted the cities of</u></b> <b><u>Norfolk and Portsmouth and it contained a window of three months during which</u></b> <b><u>targeted (+)</u> states could avoid its provisions. This document was held in reserve to avoid appearing \"the last shriek of retreat\" and was issued after the Battle of (*) </b>Antietam. For ten points, name this 1863 document released by Abraham Lincoln, which freed slaves in secessionist states.", "answer": "<b><u>Emancipation Proclamation</u></b> (or <b><u>Proclamation 95</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A woman named Dorothy Householder was the lone fatality in a July 1974</u></b> <b><u>bombing at this site. In 1952, the Kray twins were arrested after assaulting an officer</u></b> <b><u>at this location. Built on the order of William (+)</u> the Conqueror, this building was where Edward V was kept after he was declared illegitimate. Sir Walter Raleigh was (*) </b>imprisoned in this building that also held Anne Boleyn. For ten points, name this fortress and former prison that now houses Britain's Crown Jewels.", "answer": "<b><u>Tower of London</u></b> (or Her Majesty's Royal Palace and Fortress of the <b><u>Tower of</u></b> <b><u>London</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>1906 race riots in this city were sparked by the gubernatorial race between</u></b> <b><u>Hoke Smith and Clark Howell. The Rhodesian Bush War's end was negotiated by a</u></b> <b><u>politician and future mayor of this city, Andrew (+)</u> Young. The 35-year old Maynard Jackson served as mayor of this city in the 70s and 80s, when he became the first Black mayor of a major Southern city. During the U.S. Civil War, city was the starting point of Sherman's March to the Sea. Martin Luther (*) </b>King. Jr. was born in, for ten points, which Georgian metropolis?", "answer": "<b><u>Atlanta</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>At the end of this text, a man travels to reach a rainbow-colored Spindle of</u></b> <b><u>Necessity, where Ananke [[ah-NAHN-keh]], or Necessity, hands out tokens for a</u></b> <b><u>lottery. This text discusses a king of Lydia [[LIH-dee-ah]] who possessed a ring that</u></b> <b><u>grants (+)</u> invisibility. The Myth of Er and Ring of Gyges [[GY-jeez]] appear in this text, which posits a group of men who confuse shadows on a wall for reality in its Allegory of the (*) </b>Cave. Socrates speaks on the ideal \"philosopher-king\" who rules the state in, for ten points, what dialogue on government by Plato?", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Republic</u></b></em> (or <em><b><u>Politeia</u></b></em>; or <em>De</em> <em><b><u>Republic</u></b>a</em>; or <em>Plato's</em> <em><b><u>Republic</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>This figure was supposedly the ancestor of the Dorian invaders, including the</u></b> <b><u>Agiads [[ah-JEE-ids]] and Eurypontids [[yoo-rih-PON-tids]], whose dynasties co-ruled</u></b> <b><u>as kings of Sparta. The legendary progenitor of those dynasties, Hyllus [[HEE-lus]],</u></b> <b><u>was this man's son by Deianira [[dy-ah-NEE-rah]]. (+)</u> One bust of this figure identifies him with the Emperor Commodus [[KAH-moh-duss]], and a statue found in Mathura [[mah-THOO-rah]], India depicts this man slaying the Nemean [[neh-MEE-an]] (*) </b>Lion. For ten points, name this performer of Twelve Labors from Greek mythology.", "answer": "<b><u>Heracles</u></b> (accept <b><u>Hercules</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>J.A. Wayland gave this work early exposure by publishing it serially in his</u></b> <b><u>socialist paper,</u> </b><em><b><u>Appeal to Reason</u></b></em><b><u>. This work, which aimed to unveil poor working</u></b> <b><u>conditions in Chicago, (+)</u> led to its author claiming \"[he] aimed at the public's heart and by accident [he] hit it in the stomach.\" The passage of the Pure (*) </b>Food and Drug Act was partially motivated by, for ten points, which muckraking expos\u00e9 of the meatpacking industry written by Upton Sinclair?", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Jungle</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>A ceremonial bronze example of one of these objects was found in the River</u></b> <b><u>Thames [[TEMZ]] near Battersea. The</u> </b><em><b><u>aspis</u></b></em><b><u> type of these objects were also called (*)</u></b> <em><b>hoplons</b></em><b>, and a squared version called a </b><em><b>scuta</b></em><b> was used by the Romans. These items, which use a strap called a guige [[GEEJ]], can be found in heater, kite, and tower (*) </b>varieties. For ten points, name these pieces of armor held in the hand, historically used to protect from sword or spear strikes.", "answer": "<b><u>shield</u></b> (accept specific shield types like <b><u>hoplon</u></b>, <b><u>kite</u></b> shield, etc. before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}], "bonuses": []}